Inventory of the Lietuvos TSR Valstybės Saugumo Komitetas [Lithuanian KGB] selected records
Hoover Institution Archives
Lietuvos TSR Valstybės Saugumo Komitetas [Lithuanian KGB] selected records
1920-1991
2010C4
Hoover Institution Archives
1445 microfilm reels, 877 PDF files (161,277 digital pages) (161.25 linear feet)
Reports, memoranda, correspondence, lists, directives, and other documents relating to secret police, intelligence and counter-intelligence activities, dissident and anti-Soviet activities, and repatriation and nationalism issues, in Lithuania.
Lietuvos TSR Valstybės Saugumo Komitetas.
Soviet Union. Komitet gosudarstvennoĭ bezopasnosti.
Access
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2009. Several increments were received from 2010 to 2014.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Location of Originals
Lietuvos Ypatingasis Archyvas, Vilnius, Lithuania.
Related Collections
Dauzvardis (Petras Paulius) papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Gudelis (Petras) typescript, Hoover Institution Archives
Hertmanowicz (Joseph John) papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Lithuanian subject collection, Hoover Institution Archives
Terleckas (Antanas) papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Turauskas (Edvardas) papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Zukatskas (V. P.) collection, Hoover Institution Archives
Historical Note
Lithuanian branch of the Soviet secret police organization Komitet gosudarstvennoĭ bezopasnosti.
Scope and Content of Collection
This collection consists of selected opisi (records series) from what were the fifty-four opisi in Fond No. K-1, Lietuvos SSR Valstybės Saugumo Komitetas (Committee of State Security of the Lithuanian Soviet Socialist Republic, LSSR KGB), 1940-1991, held at the Lietuvos Ypatingasis Archyvas (Lithuanian special archives).
Over the years that Hoover acquired these materials, the Lithuanian special archives renamed many of the opisi in Fond K-1 and assigned them new fond and opis numbers. As a result, the materials at Hoover are described in three categories: (1) Fond No. K-1 opisi that are unchanged; (2) Fond No. K-1 opisi that Hoover received before new numbers were assigned; and (3) Fond No. K-1 opisi that Hoover received after new numbers were assigned. The numbering used at Hoover is outlined below. In all cases, the alternate numbers and titles are provided parenthetically in the series descriptions.
CATEGORY NUMBERS USED AT HOOVER ACTIONS TAKED BY LIETUVOS YPATINGASIS ARCHYVAS
1 Fond K-1, opis 10 Fond and opis numbers unchanged
2 Fond K-1, opis 2, 3, 14, 45 Renumbered as new fondy after Hoover received materials
3 Fond K-15 through K-42 (with gaps) Renumbered as new fondy before Hoover received materials
The collection contains reports, memoranda, correspondence, lists, directives, and other documents related to intelligence and counter-intelligence activities of the secret police against dissident and anti-Soviet movements and to problems with repatriation and nationalism in Lithuania.
Nearly two decades after the collapse of the Soviet Union the Lithuanian KGB-MVD archives are the largest accessible holdings of the Soviet political police (Russian holdings are for all practical purposes closed, and Ukraine just started the process of opening their KGB archives), which were left almost intact in Vilnius, Lithuania, after the disintegration of the Soviet Union. The materials document the establishment and operation of the Soviet punitive organizations from 1940 to 1991 in a key Soviet republic that was both a frontier region and a bridge to the West. They cover key subjects such as the initial annexation of the Baltic republics; World War II; the post-war struggle against anti-Soviet nationalist guerillas; collectivization of the countryside; reform of the Soviet system after Stalin's death; reactions to upheaval in Hungary in 1956, Czechoslovakia in 1968, Poland in 1980-1981, and the 1989 revolutions in Eastern Europe; reactions to increasing exposure to the West; and the final collapse of the Soviet power.
The fonds cover different aspects of the establishment, operation, and demise of the KGB in Lithuania: operational material on the struggle against individual and collective political dissent, anti-Soviet guerrillas, foreign intelligence and radio broadcasts (Fond K-1, opis 3); the NKVD-NKGB-MGB-KGB secretariat, which gathered information on political community spirit and activities from local organizations and transferred them to Moscow (Fond K-1, opis 10); political information gathered by the local NKGB-KGB departments, chiefly in Vilnius and Kaunas (Fond K-1, opis 14); a vast collection of material on dissidents, their investigation, interrogation, and trials (Fond K-1, opis 2); files pertaining to 784 convicts and listing more than 700 of those shot during 1944-1947 in the inner prison of the NKGB-MGB of the Lithuanian SSR (Fond K-15, opis 2); documents relating to inspection of surveillance-operative, counterintelligence, and investigatory work of MGB-KGB agencies of the LSSR; materials concerning inspection of punishment administration (Fond K-16, opis 1); documents relating to inspection of internal cells of the LSSR MGB and pretrial detention wards of the LSSR KGB in uezds and cities (Fond K-17, opisi 1 and 2); directives for struggle against the Lithuanian armed underground issued by the oblast level MGB directorates (Fond K-19, opis 1); directives from the SSSR NKGB-MGB-MVD relating to search of state criminals (Fond K-20, opis 1); directives of the SSSR NKVD representative for the Lithuanian SSR relating to the struggle against the armed underground (Fond K-21, opis 1); materials of special SSSR NKVD departments of the 29th territorial Red Army corps, reflecting NKVD efforts of "purging" the 29th corps (former Lithuanian army) of the "hostile and untrustworthy elements" (Fond K-22, opis 1); minutes of the Republican Commission for revision of criminal cases of persons convicted of "counterrevolutionary crimes" (Fond K-23, opis 1); reports to the Main Transport Directorate of the SSSR NKGB-KGB and correspondence with communist party institutions and Soviet authorities (Fond K-26, opis 1); orders of the director of the Lithuanian school for training operative personnel and other documents of the school (Fond K-27, opis 1); orders of the NKGB-KGB of the LSSR, its General Service Department, and the Construction Department of the LSSR MGB (Fond K-31, opis 1); working plans, memoranda, and reports prepared by MGB-KGB of the Lithuanian SSR and subdivisions of the NKVD-MVD of the Lithuanian SSR and lists of individuals arrested in Lithuania (mostly in Vilnius and Kaunas) in 1940-1941, memorandum on the activities of individuals suspected of war crimes and residing outside the Soviet Union, and other documents; (Fond K-40, opisi 1 and 2); and correspondence of USSR KGB divisions with KGB divisions in Lithuanian SSR concerning methodological literature and work with KGB cadres and plans, reports, and informational statements of the LSSR KGB subdivisions (Fond K-42, opisi 1 and 2).
In the case of the microfilm, the opisi were chosen by the Hoover Institution from records already microfilmed by the Lithuanian special archives. Before sending the microfilm to Hoover the Lithuanian special archives removed some files and pages from the microfilm. Deleted files and pages contained personal names that could not be released due to personal privacy concerns. Entire files removed from the microfilm are indicated in the reel contents list on the microfilm at the beginning of each opis. Pages removed from files on the microfilm are indicated by a splice on the microfilm, but splices can also occur for technical microfilming reasons. In many cases gaps in the sequential pagination in the original file indicate where pages were deleted, as well as how many were deleted. Pages removed from the digitized files, also due to privacy concerns, are indicated by a note in their place within the file.
Russian-language finding aids created by the Lithuanian special archives are included in the microfilm at the beginning of each opisi, in the Hoover Archives reading room, and within this file. The finding aids are arranged by file number and provide a description, number of pages, and the inclusive dates of each file.
The microfilm reel numbers used are those originally assigned by the Lithuanian special archives. They do not always run in a continuous, logical sequence, but they contain the entire opis. In addition, the microfilm often refers to the original fond and opis numbers, before the Lithuanian special archives renamed and renumbered much of the collection.
Glossary
GO
Gorodskie otdely (Municipal departments)
GUGB
Glavnoe upravlenie gosudarstvennoi bezopasnosti Main Directorate of State Security
KGB
Komitet gosudarstvennoi bezopasnosti (State Security Committee)
KGB LSSR
Komitet gosudarstvennoi bezopasnosti Litovskoi sovetskoi sotsialisticheskoi respubliki (State Security Committee of the Lithuanian Soviet Socialist Republic)
MGB
Ministerstvo gosudarstvennoi bezopasnosti (Ministry of State Security)
MVD
Ministerstvo vnutrennikh del (Ministry of Internal Affairs)
NKGB
Narodnyi kommissariat gosudarstvennoi bezopasnosti (People's Commissariat of State Security)
NKGD
Narodnyi kommissariat gosudarstvennykh del (People's Commissariat of State Affairs)
NKVD
Narodnyi kommissariat vnutrennikh del (People's Commissariat of Internal Affairs)
OGPU
Ob''edinennoe glavnoe politicheskoe upravlenie United Main Political Directorate
SSSR
Soiuz Sovetskikh sotsialisticheskikh respublik (Union of Soviet Socialist Republics)
Secret service--Soviet Union.; Police--Soviet Union.; Police--Lithuania.; Lithuania--History--Soviet occupation, 1940-1941.; Lithuania--Politics and government--1945-1991.; Nationalism--Lithuania.; Dissenters--Lithuania.
- Fond No. K-1, Lietuvos SSR Valstybės Saugumo Komitetas (Committee of State Security of the Lithuanian Soviet Socialist Republic, LSSR KGB) records, 1926-1991; 1077 microfilm reels
  - Opis 2, Records of the Counterintelligence Department of the NKVD-MGB-KGB of the LSSR, 1941-1955; 8 microfilm reels (Reel 980-987)
    Scope and Contents note
    Documents of the 3rd Department of the Directorate of State Security of the LSSR NKVD, 2nd Department of LSSR MGB, 1st Department of the LSSR MVD, and 2nd Department of the LSSR KGB relating to work with repatriates; exposure of Lithuanian, Polish, and Jewish anti-Soviet organizations; agents of foreign intelligence; the so-called "traitors to the Motherland;" and correspondence of citizens with persons abroad. Statements reflecting acceptance, transfers, and destruction of documents. Lists of repatriates, re-émigrés, and persons without citizenship. Lists of Polish refugees of 1939 who in 1940-1941 refused to accept Soviet citizenship. Accounts and special reports on subdivision of local LSSR NKVD-MGB-KGB agencies. Reports of special agents. Minutes of interrogation of arrested persons and witnesses. Reports to the Central Committee of the Communist Party of Lithuania regarding counterintelligence operations. Personal data on students of the SSSR MGB school in Lithuania.
    (Now Fond K-43, Records of the Counterintelligence Department of the NKVD-MGB-KGB of the LSSR)
    Supplemental PDF files
    Fond K-1, opis 2 Content List
    Fond K-1, opis 2 Reel Guide
  - Opis 3, Records of the Structural Divisions for Struggle against Lithuanian Nationalistic Underground and Counterintelligence Divisions of the NKVD-KGB of the LSSR, 1940-1985; 356 microfilm reels (Reel 605-960)
    Directives relating to the struggle against the armed underground. Documents concerning connection channels between Lithuanian emigration centers and the Lithuanian armed underground and radio games of the LSSR MGB with American, English, and Swedish intelligence services. Lists of combat units of the Lithuanian underground and documents relating to their investigation. Plans for cover intelligence and combat operations. Reports on elimination of the Lithuanian and Polish armed underground. Captured documents. Records of ideological counterintelligence units of the LSSR MGB-KGB concerning disclosure, interception, and prevention of anti-Soviet activities among the intelligentsia, youth, and clergy. Files of reconnaissance and sabotage groups of the NKVD that had led guerilla fighting in the rear of Nazi German troops in 1941-1944.
    (Now Fond K-41, Second Directorate of the Committee of State Security (KGB) of the Lithuanian SSR; Opis 1, Files relating to the activities [of the Second Directorate])
    Fond K-1, opis 3 Content List
    Fond K-1, opis 3 Reel Guide
  - Opis 10, Records of the Secretariat of the NKGB-MGB-KGB of the LSSR, 1940-1991; 201 microfilm reels (Reel 32-221, P216-P226)
    Correspondence with the Central Committee of the Communist Party of Lithuania, Council of People's Commissars, SSSR NKGB-KGB, and other institutions; memoranda, accounts, and other documents relating to counterintelligence and the struggle with nationalistic underground organizations led by local NKGB-KGB departments. Statements reflecting acceptance and transfer of files within the LSSR NKGB. Registers of SSSR KGB orders, resolutions, instructions and other directive documents of the LSSR KGB. Grievances and petitions from local residents. Reports submitted by the LSSR NKVD-KGB to leaders of the SSSR NKVD-KGB. Operational plans and reports of subdivisions of the LSSR NKVD-KGB. Instructions from the LSSR KGB to local KGB agencies. Orders for LSSR KGB personnel. Complaints and petitions submitted by citizens. Material on SSSR population census. Registration books for orders, directives, and instructions issued by the SSSR KGB and LSSR KGB.
    Fond K-1, opis 10 Content List
    Fond K-1, opis 10 Reel Guide
    Fond K-1, opis 10 Missing Files List
  - Opis 14, Records of City Departments of the NKGB-KGB of the LSSR, 1944-1987; 94 microfilm reels (Reel 511-603, 1000)
    Working plans of city departments of the LSSR NKVD-KGB in Vilnius, Kaunas, Klaipėda, Šiauliai, and Panevėžys. Reports to the leadership of the LSSR NKGB-KGB. Correspondence of city departments with LSSR NKGB-KGB agencies and local party authorities. Complaints and petitions submitted by citizens, with related materials. Records on economical-financial activities of city departments of the LSSR NKGB-KGB. Registration books, statements reflecting acceptance and transfer of files within departments and destruction of documents.
    (Now Fond K-18, Records of city departments of the Committee of State Security (KGB) of the Lithuanian SSR; Opis 1, Files relating to the activities [of the city departments])
    Fond K-1, opis 14 Content List
    Fond K-1, opis 14 Reel Guide
    Fond K-1, opis 14 Missing Files List
  - Opis 45, Permanent records management files, NKVD-NKGB-MGB-KGB of the LSSR, 1926-1991; 418 microfilm reels (Reel 1081-1495, 1498, A-139, A-140)
    Permanent record management files of the LSSR NKVD-NKGB-MGB-KGB and local agencies of the SSSR OGPU-GUGB-NKVD-MGB-KGB concerning cultural, political, and public figures of the First Lithuanian Republic, leaders of the Lithuanian Catholic Church, "white insurgents" of 1941, post-war Lithuanian guerilla fighters, residents of Lithuania, suspected of collaboration with German occupation authorities or special services of Nazi Germany, fighters of Armia Krajowa, participants in Lithuanian and Polish anti-Soviet organization, refugees who tried to flee abroad, and other so-called state criminals.
    (Now Fond K-30, Permanent records management files of the Committee of State Security (KGB) of the Lithuanian SSR, Opis 1, Permanent records management files)
    Fond K-1, opis 45 Content List
    Fond K-1, opis 45 Reel Guide
    Fond K-1, opis 45 Missing Files List
- Fond No. K-15, Records of the 10th Department of the Committee of State Security (KGB) of the Lithuanian SSR, 1940-1991; 24 digital files (Reading room workstation)
  - Opis 2, Copies of documents on execution of death penalties, 1944-1947; 24 digital files
    Historical note
    The files in this opis pertain to 784 convicts and list more than 700 of those shot from 1944 to 1947 in the inner prison of the NKGB-MGB of the Lithuanian SSR. Most of the people executed were participants in the June 1941 uprising, policemen, and soldiers in Lithuanian self-defense battalions from 1941 to 1944. Others shot in the inner prison of the NKVD–MGB, though fewer in number, were soldiers of former Lithuanian battalions fighting with German troops, agents of special troops in Germany, participants in the extermination of Jews, Lithuanian and Polish postwar guerilla fighters, and other convicts. The majority of those executed were Lithuanian; others included Byelorussians, Poles, Germans, Russians, Ukrainians, and Latvians. Access to the documents is limited in accordance with the laws of the Lithuanian Republic.
    This opis includes twenty files, arranged chronologically by the earliest dated record in the original file, consisting of copies of the following records:
    - Correspondence of department A of the NKGB-MGB of the Lithuanian SSR, mainly concerning reports of Department A to Soviet military tribunals on carrying out death penalties
    - Records containing information on executions (in many cases with the name and occupation of the executioner)
    - Memos from chairs of military tribunals to Department A requesting directives to carry out the death penalty
    - Memos to chiefs of prisons requesting transfer of convicts to the commandant of the NKVD-MVD of the Lithuanian SSR
    - Directives from the chief of the Military Collegium of the USSR Supreme Court to the chair of the Military Tribunal of the troops of the NKVD-MVD of the Lithuanian SSR regarding the death penalty, along with copies of cover letters.
    Also included in this opis are four files consisting of a card catalog listing individuals convicted by the military tribunal.
    (Formerly Fond K-1, Opis 6)
    Supplemental PDF file
    Fond K-15, opis 2 Content List
- Fond No. K-16, Records of the Inspectorate under the Chair of the Committee of State Security (KGB) of the Lithuanian SSR, 12 microfilm reels
  - Opis 1, Files relating to the activities [of the Inspectorate], 1946-1958; 12 microfilm reels (Reel 988-999)
    Documents relating to inspection of surveillance-operative, counterintelligence, and investigatory work of MGB-KGB agencies of the LSSR. Materials concerning inspection of punishment administration.
    (Formerly Fond K-1, Opis 11, Records of the Inspectorate under the Chair of the KGB of the LSSR)
    Fond K-16, opis 1 Content List
    Fond K-16, opis 1 Reel Guide
- Fond No. K-17, Records of the Pretrial Detention Center of the Committee of State Security (KGB) of the Lithuanian SSR, 23 microfilm reels
  - Opis 1, Office records, 1944-1991; 13 microfilm reels (Reel 276-278, 279A, 961-967, 969, 970 (part))
    Records of the Prison Department and Internal Prison of the LSSR MGB and Pretrial Detention Ward of the LSSR KGB. Documents relating to inspection of internal cells of the LSSR MGB and pretrial detention wards of the LSSR KGB in uezds and cities. Correspondence relating to prisoners and operative work. Lists of prisoners and investigatory files. Various informational statements.
    (Formerly Fond K-1, Opis 13, Pretrial Detention Center of the KGB of the LSSR: Office records; Prisoners' personal files)
    Fond K-17, opis 1 Content List
    Fond K-17, opis 1-2 Reel Guide
  - Opis 2, Prisoners' personal files, 1944-1990; 10 microfilm reels (Reel 970 (part), 971-979)
    Prisoners' personal files. Records of valuables seized from prisoners.
    Fond K-17, opis 2 Content List
- Fond No. K-19, Records of oblast level Directorates of the Ministry of State Security (MGB) of the Lithuanian SSR, 212 microfilm reels
  - Opis 1, Files relating to the activities [of the oblast level directorates], 1949-1953; 212 microfilm reels (Reel 279-487, 604, 1001-1002)
    Directives for struggle against the Lithuanian armed underground issued by the LSSR MGB directorates in Vilnius, Kaunas, Klaipėda, and Šiauliai to LSSR MGB departments in raions. Correspondence. Reports from MGB departments in raions relating to elimination of the armed underground and counterintelligence work and operations concerning search for state criminals. Lists of Lithuanian guerilla fighters and personnel of MGB directorates in oblasts.
    (Formerly Fond K-1, Opis 16, Records of the oblast level directorates of the MGB-MVD of the LSSR)
    Fond K-19, opis 1 Content List
    Fond K-19, opis 1 Reel Guide
    Fond K-19, opis 1 Missing Files List
- Fond No. K-20, Records of the Fourth Department of the Ministry of State Security (MGB) of the Lithuanian SS, 31 microfilm reels
  - Opis 1, Files relating to the activities [of the Fourth Department], 1943-1953; 31 microfilm reels (Reel 241-271)
    Directives from the SSSR NKGB-MGB-MVD relating to search of state criminals. Reports, correspondence statements lists of prisoners, and other office documents of the LSSR NKGB-MVD reflecting their work in the search of state criminals (mostly residents of Lithuania under suspicion of collaborating with German authorities or intelligence services of Nazi Germany).
    (Formerly Fond K-1, Opis 17, Records of the Second Department of the NKGB-MGB of the LSSR; Records of the Fourth Department of the NKGB-MGB of the LSSR)
    Fond K-20, opis 1 Content List
    Fond K-20, opis 1 Reel Guide
- Fond No. K-21, Records of the Operative Departments of the SSSR Ministry of Internal Affairs (MVD) and the Ministry of State Security (MGB), 20 microfilm reels
  - Opis 1, Files relating to the activities [of the Operative Departments], 1943-1953; 20 microfilm reels (Reel 221-240)
    Directives of the SSSR NKVD representative for the Lithuanian SSR relating to the struggle against the armed underground. Directives to the LSSR NKVD-NKGB departments in uezds from heads of operative departments of the NKVD-NKGB. Reports reflecting the struggle of LSSR NKVD-NKGB departments in uezds, NKVD troops, and operative departments of the NKVD-NKGB against the Lithuanian/Polish armed underground. Captured documents.
    (Formerly Fond K-1, Opis 18, Records of the Operative Departments of the SSSR NKVD-NKGB in Lithuania)
    Fond K-21, opis 1 Content List
    Fond K-21, opis 1 Reel Guide
- Fond No. K-22, Records of the Special Department of the SSSR People's Commissariat of Internal Affairs (NKVD) of the 29th Rifle Corps of the Baltic Military District (Okrug), 1 microfilm reel
  - Opis 1, Files relating to the activities [of the Special Department], 1940-1941; 1 microfilm reel (Reel 488)
    Documents of special SSSR NKVD departments of the 29th territorial Red Army corps, reflecting NKVD efforts of "purging" the 29th corps (former Lithuanian army) of the "hostile and untrustworthy elements."
    (Formerly Fond K-1, Opis 19, Special Records of the NKVD Department of the Baltic Military Okrug)
    Fond K-22, opis 1 Content List
    Fond K-22, opis 1 Reel Guide
- Fond No. K-23, Records of the Republican Commission of the Committee of State Security (KGB) of the Lithuanian SSR for Revision of Criminal Cases of Persons Kept in Camps, Colonies, and Prisons of the SSSR MVD or in Exile in Special Settlements for Counterrevolutionary Crime, 26 microfilm reels
  - Opis 1, Files relating to the activities [of the Republican Commission], 1949-1953; 26 microfilm reels (Reel 1-26)